Guide to the Hugo Kauder Papers 1927-1946
University of Chicago Library
Kauder, Hugo. Papers
1927-1946
1 linear ft. (2 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Hugo Kauder, composer, musician. The Hugo Kauder Papers and Addenda includes records, holograph manuscript scores, reproduced manuscript scores, and published scores. Many of the scores reproduced by blueprint process bear holograph revisions or dynamic markings in pen or pencil, and a number of scores are inscribed to Edward E. Lowinsky and his family. This collection has been assigned Codex Manuscript #1399.
Information on Use
Access
Audio recordings in Series I are restricted due to the need for special equipment.
Biographical Note
Hugo Kauder (1888–1972) was an Austrian and American composer and musical pedagogue. A self-taught musician, Kauder's chamber music compositions are contrapuntal and characterized by conservative harmonies and closed scales. Kauder published two works on music theory, Entwurf einer neuen Melodie- und Harmonielehre (Vienna, 1932), and Counterpoint: An Introduction to Polyphonic Composition (New York, 1960). Forced in 1938 to leave Vienna where he was a member of the Konzertverein Orchestra, he settled in New York in 1940 and spent the rest of his career composing and teaching there.
Scope Note
The Hugo Kauder Papers and Addenda includes records, holograph manuscript scores, reproduced manuscript scores, and published scores. Many of the scores reproduced by blueprint process bear holograph revisions or dynamic markings in pen or pencil, and a number of scores are inscribed to Edward E. Lowinsky and his family.
The Kauder Papers are arranged in five series: Series I: Phonograph Records; Series II: Holograph Manuscript Scores; Series III: Reproduction Manuscript Scores; Series IV: Published Music; Series V: Addenda Manuscript Scores and Essays. This collection has been assigned Codex Manuscript #1399.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Kauder, Hugo, 1888-; Lowinsky, Edward; Music–Manuscripts; Music–Manuscripts
INVENTORY
- Series I: Phonograph Records
  - Sonata for English horn and Piano; and Improvisation for English Horn Alone. Boston: Night Music Recording Company, 1946. NM 105 108. Two 10" discs, four sides. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Holograph Manuscript Scores
  - Capriccio. [String trio]. 1927. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Preludium und Fuge. [Piano]. June 30, 1939. 2 copies with slight variations and revisions; apparently older version marked "VII" (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sonate in A für Violine und Klavier. 1939. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Prüludium und Fuge (III) [G minor, piano]. 1939. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sonate für das Klavier, I. Satz. Christmas, 1940. Inscribed "Eduard Lowinsky herzlichst HK" (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Zweite Sonate für das Klavier. Für Eduard Lowinsky. March 12, 1941. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Prüludium und Fuge. [G major, piano]. Undated. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Prüludium und Fuge. [F# major, piano]. Undated. Inscribed "Herzlichsten Gruss! HK" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Kleine Suite für Violine Bratsche und Violincell. [with separate parts]. Undated. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - IV. Streichquartett, 2. Satz. Undated. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - V. Streichquartett, I. Satz. Dated May 23, no year. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Konzert für Bratsche und Streichorchester. [Piano reduction with separate viola part]. Undated. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Zweite Kleine Suite für Violine und Klavier. [With separate violin part]. Undated. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Drei Kinderlieder. Undated. Inscribed "Eduard und Grete Lowinsky, für Naomi" (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series III: Reproduction Manuscript Scores
  - Ein neues Geigebüchlein: Sieben Sonaten für die Geige allein, Sonate für zwei Geigen, Sonate für drei Geigen. 1931. Autograph revisions in pen. Autograph manuscript: Sonate für zwei Geigen, 2. Geigenstimme für Cello eine Oktave tiefer. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Vom Leiden. [Song, words by Albert Verwey]. May 26, 1932. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Prelude, Passacaglia and Fugue for the Organ. July 27, 1935. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Gesang der Geister über den Wassern. [Song, words by Goethe]. August 16, 1937. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Sonate für Viola und Klavier. 1938. Manuscript performance markings in pencil. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Two Songs (Poems by W. B. Yeats): The Everlasting Voices; Had I the Heaven's Embroidered Cups. January 30 and May 7, 1939. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Abbitte. [Song, words by Hölderlin]. April 20, 1939. Negative photostat. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - I. Sonate für das Klavier. New York, October 21, 1940. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Sonate für zwei Geigen. November 26, 1940. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Loesung. [Song, words by Rudolf Pannwitz]. May 11, 1941.Sternenmoral. [Song, words by Nietsche]. May 30, 1941. 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - III. Kleine Suite. [For violin and piano; separate violin part]. July 11, 1941. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Vierte Kleine Suite für Violine und Klavier. [With separate violin part]. August 8, 1941. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Dritte Sonate. [Piano]. New York, December 20, 1941. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - The Everlasting Voices. [Song, words by W. B. Yeats. A five-part version which differs markedly from the 1939 one-part version in 'Folder 21]. January 24, 1942. Two Copies (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Seventh String Quartet. New York, July 30, 1942. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Toccata für das Klavier. November 3, 1942. Inscribed "Herzlichsten Gruss! 9.11.42 HK" (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Sonate für zwei Violinen. 1942. Manuscript revision in pen. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Sonate für Horn und Klavier, Willem Valkenier zugeeignet. [Separate horn part]. New York, February 5, 1943. Manuscript revisions in pen and dynamic markings in pencil. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Sonatine für das Klavier. New York, February 27, 1943. Manuscript revisions in pen; six staves of manuscript revisions on cardboard. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Klavierbüchlein (The Piano Book) I. 1943. Manuscript revisions in pen. Inscribed "Herzlichen Gruss! HK" (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Klavierbüchlein (The Piano Book) II. 1943. Manuscript revisions in pen. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Eighth Quartet. October 14, 1944. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Drei Choralvorspiele für die Orgel. 1944. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Trio, Erwin Bodky zugeeignet. [Violin, `cello, piano; separate parts]. May 27, 1945. Manuscript dynamic markings in pen. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Sonata for English Horn and Piano, to Mr. Louis Speyer. [Separate English horn part]. 1946. Manuscript revisions in pencil. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Serenade für Flöte Violine Viola. [Separate parts]. 1947. Manuscript revisions in pen. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Vierte Sonate für das Klavier, für Lilian Kallir. March 28, 1948. Manuscript revisions in pen on cardboard pasted over one and a half staves on p. 5. (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Kleine Suite: Fünf Stücke aus dem Geigenbüchlein für Violine und Klavier. [Separate parts]. Undated, [ca. 1931?] performance markings in pencil. (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Song from `Deirdre' (W. B. Yeats). [Flute, voice and harp]. Undated. Manuscript revision in pen; two copies. (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Zwei Sprüche. [Songs, words by Hölderlin]. Undated. Zigeunerlied. [Song, words by Goethe]. Undated. Negative photostat.Three English Folksongs (arranged by Hugo Kauder). Undated. (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Series IV: Published Music
  - Streichquartett C Moll (Vienna: Universal-Edition, 1922). Inscribed "Herzlichen Gruss! HK" Sieben Lieder für eine Singstimme mit Klavier-beglietung (Vienna: By the composer, 1928). Inscribed "Eduard Lowinsky und den seinen aufs herzlichste August 1939 HK" (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Chorbüchlein, Erstes Heft (Vienna: Universal-Edition, 1937).Twaalf Gedichten/Zwölf Gedichte (Santpoort: C. A. Mees, 1939). Words by Albert Verwey, translated into German by Stefan George and Rudolf Pannwitz. One voice with piano. (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Die Suche nach dem Traum / In Search of a Dream (Peking: Die Pappelinsel Werkstatt / The Poplar Island Press, n.d.) Words from drama, "The Return of the Soul" by T'ang Hsien-Tzu, German and English versions by Vincenz Hundhausen. For two female voices and piano. Inscribed "Eduard Lowinsky herzlichst New York, Mürz 1941 Hugo Kauder" (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Series V: Addenda Manuscript Scores and Essays
  - "Who Goes With Fergus?" (W. B. Yeats). For two sopranos and an alto. Undated. Two copies. (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - "Three Canons." For soprano and alto. Undated. Eleven copies. (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - "Three Little Tailors." For two sopranos and an alto. Undated. Ten copies. (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - "Die Nachtigall." (Goethe). For flute, soprano, and alto. (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - "Psalm CXLVIII, 1-4." For soprano, alto, and bass. (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - "Musik als Zeit-und Raumkunst. Fragmente." T.D., 2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - "Musiealische Bildung." T.D., 3 pp. (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - "Musik und Dichtung." T.D., 4 pp. (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - "Das Aussehmusikalische in Der Musik. Fragmente." T.D., 3 pp. (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - "Volkslied und Kunstlied." T.D., 2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 52)